A Guide to the Marcia A. T. Thompson papers FA1489
Rockefeller Archive Center
Marcia A. T. Thompson papers
1936-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Thompson, Marcia
New York City Ballet
National Arts Stabilization Fund
Ford Foundation
FA1489
13.75 Cubic Feet 35 boxes (30 letter document containers and 5 legal document containers)
Biographical / Historical
Marcia Aldrich Thompson Thompson (1923-2018) was an advocate for financial stabilization projects in the arts throughout her long career with the Ford Foundation, the National Arts Stabilization Fund, and as a board member for many arts organizations. She was born on Oct. 2, 1923 in Hankow, China. Thompson attended the Columbia University School of General Studies, the New School for Social Research, and earned a certificate from Katherine Gibbs School. She started her career at the New York Times as the Assistant to the Sunday Editor from 1946-1951. She moved on to hold multiple positions at the International Press Institute as Assistant to the Chairman and Associate Director, Conference Coordinator until 1953. In 1955, she married Ralph Thompson, a book critic and columnist for the New York Times, and secretary of the Book‐of‐the-Month Club.
In 1953, Thompson joined the Ford Foundation as a program officer. From the beginning, she was involved in the formation and development of the Foundation's program in humanities and the arts. She had a hand in all major subsequent initiatives through 1983, including the development of programs for individual artists as well as institutional development in the arts. She worked to create incentives for symphonies, ballet companies, theaters and other arts groups to liquidate their deficits and build working capital reserves. Some of her achievements include: providing $80.2 million in grants to orchestras across the country as part of the Symphony Orchestra Program, providing support for development of dance companies and professional training in classical dance, and developing the Program for Administrative Interns, the Program for Curatorial Training, and the Program for Catalogues of American Fine Arts Collections. She also led the Ford Foundation Cash Reserve Program from which the National Arts Stabilization Fund eventually evolved. She collaborated closely with Ford Foundation executive William W. McPeak and Vice President W. McNeil Lowry. Lowry and Thompson's partnership helped Ford become the country's largest nongovernmental arts patron and the first to support dance. By 1967, Thompson was the Ford Foundation's senior program officer in the arts and humanities.
Thompson left the Ford Foundation to found and serve as president of the National Arts Stabilization Fund (NASF) in December 1983. The NASF was created with funding from the Ford Foundation, the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, and the Rockefeller Foundation, to provide arts institutions with grants and fiscal management strategies. Thompson was responsible for all aspects of the NASF's operations including development of principles and policies, fundraising, project development and oversight, administration, planning, board relations and external affairs until 1991. She served as Chairman of the Executive Committee and Vice Chairman of the NASF from 1991-1993. Thompson was also a board member of the School of American Ballet, Theater for a New Audience and the Scherman Foundation. Marcia Thompson died in March 2018.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series:
1. Trude Lash Fellowship Program, 2004-2006
2. Personal Correspondence, Newsletters, and Reports, 1973-2004
3. Arts Stabilization Projects, 1936-2000
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the personal and professional files of Marcia T. Thompson, longtime promoter of financial stabilization projects in the arts. The collection includes reports and correspondence related to the Trude Lash Fellowship Program, reports and correspondence from Thompson's time at the Ford Foundation, and financial reports, correspondence, and long-term planning materials from the National Arts Stabilization Fund (NASF). There are many files related to the School of American Ballet, the New York City Ballet, and arts stabilization projects in major cities across the United States.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated and transferred to the RAC in 2018 by Janet E. Merrill, Executor of the Marcia Thompson Estate, and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2018:130.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Related Materials
Ford Foundation records, Arts and Humanities Program Files, Marcia T. Thompson (FA1482)
Arts -- Finance; Ballet; Ballet companies -- United States -- Finance; Ford Foundation; Performing arts -- United States; Symphony orchestras -- United States; Theatre
- Trude Lash Fellowship Program, 2004-2006; 1; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Lash - Fundraising, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lash - Steering Committee Minutes, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lash - Selection Committee, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lash - Steering Committee, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lash - Memorandum of Understanding for The Steering Committee of the Trude Lash Fellowship Program, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fund for Social Change, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lash - Application Materials, 2001-2006 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Lash - Correspondence, Call for Applicants, Application Background Materials, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
- Personal Correspondence, Newsletters, and Reports, 1973-2004; 2; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  - Arts Organizations Newsletters, Real Estate Documents, and Magazine Clippings, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Scope and Contents
    Materials related to Central Park Views, the School of American Ballet, Park Avenue Real Estate Lyric Opera, Dartmouth Alumni, Theatre Communications Group, Corporate Council for the Arts, Campaign for Thirteen WNET
  - Foundation Reports and Correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Includes: 1988 NACUBO Endowment Study: Executive Summary; Oregon Arts Commission; National Arts Stabilization Fund; Endowment Issues; Managing Foundation Assets, The Foundation Center; Council on Foundations; Managing Endowment Funds for Arts Organizations
  - Endowments Issues, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Memo - Notes on Endowment Self-Evaluation Issues
    American Symphony Orchestra League Conference -1989
    NASF Spending Policy
    Articles Regarding Endowment Spending
    Special Report on the Finance Committee: The High Art of Strategic, Directors and Boards
  - Personal Correspondence and Newsletters, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Personal correspondence with David Hawkanson of the Guthrie Theater (MN) and Robert F. Branscombe
    Clippings and materials related to the Hacienda Del Sol in Tucson
    NASF Press Release - Opera/Columbus Awarded First Stabilization Grant
    The New York Committee of the Garden Club of America newsleter, 2000
    Guthrie Theater Report, 1996-1998 and news clippings
  - Museum of Fine Arts - Newsletters and Reports, 1975-1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Danny Newman and the Lyric Opera of Chicago, 1991-2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    File also includes 3 issues of The Livable City, A Publication of the Municipal Art Society (1991-1993)
  - The Carlisle Project: A Center for Choreographic Development and Professional Ballet Studies, Barbara Weisberger, Artistic Director, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Danny Newman - Correspondence, Clippings, and Drafts (4 folders), 1981-2004 (Box 2, Folder 18, Box 3, Folder 19-21)
    Note from folder: Danny Newman of the Lyric Opera of Chicago, good friend of Marcia, met doing stabilization of the arts
  - Michael George, Freelance Photographer - Reviews in Publications and CV, 1973-1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Michael George Photography - Photographic Book Projects - CV and Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Arts Stabilization Projects, 1936-2000; 3; 12.99 Cubic Feet 28 letter document boxes and 5 legal document boxes
  This series includes reports, correspondence, clippings, and speeches related to arts stabilization projects at the National Arts Stabilization Fund and various Ford Foundation programs. There are a number of reports and correspondence from Marcia Thompson's board membership with the School of American Ballet
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - List of Press Releases, 1993 December (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Investment and Financial Strategy Materials, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ten Years of Service to Arts Organizations, National Arts Stabilization Fund, circa 1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund: The First Phase (2 copies), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - National Arts Stabilization in Arizona: A Report to the Community, The Flinn Foundation, circa 1997 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Arizona Project, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund Seattle Program, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - The National Arts Stabilization Fund, Inc. - Meeting of the Finance Committee - Dec. 7, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - To-Do Lists, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund Board of Directors Meetings and Grant Documents, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Recommended Grant Actions Documents for:
    Ballet Arizona
    Phoenix Symphony Association
    Maryland Institute, College of Art
    Baltimore Opera Company, Inc.
    Kansas City Art Institute
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Ford Foundation Symphony Orchestra Program Analysis, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Mellon Foundation Analysis, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Reports and Correspondence with Grantees/Partner Organizations (2 folders), 1983-1992 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
    Folder 36:
    Correspondence with:
    Empire Brass Quintet
    Fuller Museum of Art
    Handel and Hadyn Society
    Boston University Theatre
    Institute of Contemporary Art
    New England Conservatory
    Greater Boston Arts Fund
    Massachsetts Council on the Arts and Humanities
    Hall Family Foundations
    Clearinghouse for Midcontinent Foundations
    Arizona Academy
    Tucson Symphony Orchestra
    Illinois Arts Foundation
    Actors Theatre of Louisville
    Albany Museum of Art
    Alliance of Independent Colleges of Art
    Amas Repertory Theatre
    American Place Theatre
    The Atlanta Opera
    Ballet Oklahoma
    BankAmerica Foundation
    Berkely Repertory Theatre
    The British Council
    Brooklyn Academy of Music
    Brooklyn Children's Museum
    Folder 37:
    Cedar Rapids Marion Arts Council
    Department of Cultural Affairs, Chicago
    Cincinnati Art Museum
    Clear Lake Chamber Music Society
    Colorado Council on the Arts and Humanities
    Colorado Music Festival
    Opera Colorado
    Colorado Philharmonic Orchestra
    Colorado Springs Symphony
    Community Foundation of Greater Washington (DC)
    Contemporary Arts Museum (Houston)
    D-Art Visual Art Center
    Dayton Performing Arts Fund
    The Duluth Playhouse
    Ohio Arts Council
    Eugene Arts Foundation
    Eugene Ballet Company
    Film Forum
    Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco
    The Edison Institute: Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village
    Frederick Gash Foundation
    Gannett Foundation
    The Goodman Theatre
    LaClaire Portraiture
    Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum
    Howard Heinz Endowment
    William and Flora Hewlett Foundation
    The Dun and Bradstreet Corporation
    Indiana Repertory Theatre
    The James Irvine Foundation
    The JBSpeed Art Museum
    Just Causes
    Peter Kiewit Foundation
    Knight Foundation
    Knoxville Opera Company
    Samuel H. Kress Foundation
    La Mama Etc.
    Medicine Show Theatre Ensemble
    Memphis Arts Council
    Miami City Ballet
    Middlesex County Cultural and Heritage Commission
    Minnesota Council on Foundations
    Music-Theatre Group
    National Public Radio
    Opera Theatre of Saint Louis
    Opinion Research Association, Inc.
    The Oram Group
    Orange County Performing Arts Center
    Ordway Music Theatre
    National Dance Institute
    ATT Foundation
    Education and Culture Committee: A Supplement to Part II: Results
    Ford Foundation
  - Ford Foundation Stabilization Program - Education and Culture Committee: A Supplement to Part II, Results, 1982 March (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Clippings and Miscellaneous Documents, 1983-1993 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Includes:
    Blank form - Summary of Pertinent Operating Data
    Administrative Officer Job Responsibilities Description
    1984 calendar printout January-May
    New York Grantmakers in the Arts contact list
  - Dance Newsletters, 1974-1991 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Ford Foundation Arts and Humanities Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Contains 1974 staff lists for:
    The American Conservatory Theatre
    Arena Stage
    Cincinnati Playhouse
    City Center of Music and Drama
    Denver Symphony Association
    Foundation for American Dance/City Center Joffrey Ballet
    Harlem School for the Arts
    The Loretto Hilton Repertory Theatre
    The Repertory Theatre
    New York Shakespeare Festival
    Pennsylvania Ballet Association
    San Francisco Opera
    School of American Ballet
    Mark Taper Forum
    Theatre Development Fund
  - Ford Foundation Programs I and II At-a-Glance Index, 1984-1993 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Distributions, 1994-1996 (Box 34, Folder 350)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Confidential Materials
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund 403(b), 1993 (Box 34, Folder 351)
    Confidential
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund Deferred Comp/Interest, 1987-1994 (Box 34, Folder 352)
    Confidential Material
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund 401(k), 1992-1993 (Box 34, Folder 353)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund 401(a), 1987-1996 (Box 34, Folder 354)
  - Memos and Correspondence, 1976-1997 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Holy Cross Abbey, 1979-1993 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Clippings, Postcards, Correspondence, and Newsletters (4 folders), 1936-1990 (Box 5, Folder 45-48)
  - Project Comments, 1984-1993 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    New York City Project Comments Binder -
    1. Alvin Ailey
    2. Ballet Hispanico
    3. Boys Choir of Harlem
    4. Bronx Museum of the Arts
    5. Caribbean Cultural Center
    6. Dance Theatre of Harlem
    7. El Museo del Barrio
    8. Harlem School of the Arts
    9. INTAR
    10. Jamaica Arts Center
    11. Jazzmobile
    12. Pan Asian Repertory Theatre
    13. Puerto Rican Traveling Theatre
    14. Repertorio Espanol
    15. Studio Museum in Harlem
    16. New York City Project Committee
    17. New York City Project Donors
    18. Other
    Kansas City Project Comments Binder
    1. Kansas City Art Institute
    2. Kansas City Symphony
    3. Lyric Opera of Kansas City
    4. Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art
    5. State Ballet of Missouri
    6. Kansas City Project Committee
    7. Kansas City Donors
    8. Other
    Boston Project Comments Binder
    1. American Repertory Theatre
    2. Boston Ballet
    3. Boston CAMERATA
    4. Boston Concert Opera
    5. Boston Film/Video Foundation
    6. Boston Shakespeare Company
    7. Concert Dance Company
    8. Danforth Museum of Art
    9. DeCordova Museum and Dana Museum
    10. Empire Brass Quintet
    11. Fuller Museum of Art
    12. Handel and Haydn Society
    13. Huntington Theatre Company
    14. Institute of Contemporary Art
    15. New England Conservatory
    16. Boston Project Committee
    17. Boston Project Donor
  - Dance Data Analysis, 1984 April (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Ford Foundation Stabilization Program, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Endowment Analysis, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Stabilization I and II - Recisions and Default Records, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - New Century Program For the American Theatre - Long Range Plan, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Theatre Communications Group - The Century Program for the American Theatre, Celebrating Artists and Inspiring Excellence in Theatre for a Culturally Diverse Society, Summary Draft Case Statement, 1991 February 12 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Ballet Development Activities, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Resident Theater Data, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Opera Data 1982 and 1983, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Symphony Orchestras (2 folders), 1965-1985 (Box 7, Folder 59-60)
  - National Arts Stabilization/National Arts Stabilization Fund - Correspondence, Conference Materials, Financial Materials, and Awards, 1994-1996 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Ford Documents - Case for Formation of the National Arts Stabilization Fund, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Ford Foundation - The Stabilization Strategy, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Ford Foundation Documents Regarding Formation of the National Arts Stabilization Fund, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    Drafts of the NASF Executive Summary, correspondence, and Building on Experience: An Opportunity - The Case for a National Arts Stabilization Fund, NASF 5-Year Preliminary Projects, and memos
  - National Arts Stabilization/National Arts Stabilization Fund - Administrative Files, Articles, Reports, and Press Kit Materials (2 folders), 1979-1999 (Box 7, Folder 65-66)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Press Releases and Financial Materials, 1978-1999 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Blank Year-to-Date Financial Highlight Summary Forms and Fiscal Year End Financial Highlight Summary Forms, Financial Statements, etc. (2 folders), 1989-1995 (Box 8, Folder 68-69)
  - Rethinking Stabilization: Strengthening Arts Organizations During Times of Change: Discussion Draft, Prepared by Strategic Grantmaker Services, Jane Culbert, William Keens, Laura Lewis Mandeles, Thomas Wolf, 1995 May (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Notes and Budget Materials, 1985-1991 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - 1984 Application to MacArthur Foundation (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 72-73)
    September 18, 1984 Letter
    1. NASF Board of Directors
    2. NASF Summary of Objectives
    3. Summary of Impact and Advantages of Corporate and Foundation Support of NASF Strategy
    4. National Response to Establishment of NASF
    5. Greater Boston Arts Fund December 12, 1983 news release [excerpted]
    6. GABF Officers and Members of the Board
    7. Boston Stabilization Project: Commitment of Local Donors
    8. Initial Reactions to Announcement of GBAF
    9. NASF Preliminary Eligibility Requirements
    10. The Stabilization Strategy: What It Is and How It Works
    11. Financial Forecasts and Reports
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - 1984 Status Report to Mellon Foundation, 1984 April (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - 1984 Proposal to Rockefeller Foundation for a (Second) Grant ($500,000 Requested), 1984 June-October (Box 8, Folder 75)
    1. Purpose
    2. The Need
    3. The Stabilization Strategy
    4. What NASF's Strategy Can Achieve
    5. Organizational Activities
    6. Greater Boston Stabilization Campaign
    7. Plans for the Future
    8. Financial Forecasts and Reports
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Fine Arts Museums Foundation - Investment Review, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Blank Accounting and Financial Management Forms and Checklists, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Applause (Positive Responses to the National Arts Stabilization Fund), 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Congratulatory Letters, 1978-1987 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Lila Wallace-Reader's Digest Fund - New York Multicultural Project, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Organization Inventories/Profile Sheets, 1984-1989 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Policy and Planning Committee - Five-Year Commitment Schedule and Analysis, 1984 September 20 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Policy and Planning Committee Meeting Minutes and Supplemental Documents, 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    NASF Policy and Planning Committee Meeting Minutes, September 20, 1984
    General Accomplishments, 1983-1989
    NASF National Leveraging Pool
    Report to the Ford Foundation, April 26, 1985
    Revenue and Expense Projections, August 1983
    Correspondence regarding Studio Museum in Harlem and potential Pennsylvania stabilization fund
    NASF Executive Summary
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Background Information, 1984 November (Box 9, Folder 84)
    Tab 1: NASF's Purpose
    Tab 2: The Need
    Tab 3: The Stabilization Strategy: What It Is, How It Works and How It Evolved
    Tab 4: What the Strategy Can Achieve
    Tab 5: NASF's First Project: The Greater Boston Stabilization Campaign
    Tab 6: Plans for the Future
    Tab 7: Impact and Advantages of Support of NASF Strategy
    Tab 8: Appendix A: Release Announcing Formation of NASF [Excerpted Version]
    Tab 9: Appendix B: Highlights of National Response to Establishment of NASF
    Tab 10: Appendix C: NASF's Primary Objective
    Tab 11: Appendix D: The Stabilization Process
    Tab 12: Appendix E: NASF's Preliminary Eligibility Requirements
    Tab 13: Appendix F: The Stabilization Strategy: What It Is and How It Works
    Tab 14: Appendix G: The Stabilization Strategy 1971-1981: A Decade's Report, Geographical Listing of Stabilization Grantees, 1971-1981
    Tab 15: Appendix H: Greater Boston Arts Fund 1983 Release [Excerpted Version], Initial Reaction to the Release: A Sampling, Greater Boston Arts Fund Board, Greater Boston Stabilization Campaign Donors
    Tab 16: Appendix I: NASF's Tax Status
    Tab 17: Appendix J: Financial Data
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Background Information (2 copies), 1985 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund, 1983 June (Box 9, Folder 86)
    Table of Contents:
    Executive Summary
    Purpose
    The Problem
    The Stabilization Strategy
    Potential Sources of Support
    Structure, Leadership, and Staff
    5-Year Revenue and Expense Projections:
    Schedule I - Summary Revenues and Expense Projections
    Schedule II - Projected Revenue - Details
    Scheudle III - Sources and Use of Funds Projection
    Schedule IV - Year I Operating Expenses
    Schedule V - Transitional and Start-Up Costs
    Schedule VI - Budget Assumptions
    Appendix A: The Stabilization Strategy: What It Is and How It Works
    Appendix B: An Interim Report 1971-1981
    Appendix C: Participants in the Ford Program
    Appendix D: Geographical Distribution of Participants in the Ford Program
    Appendix E: Preliminary Eligibility Considerations Key Criteria for Evaluation
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Executive Summary, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Long-Range Strategic Plan (1993-1997), 1993 March (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Greater Boston Stabilization Project - Results and Evaluations, 1988-1993 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Boston Project Status Reports - Nominees Evaluation, 1986-1988 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Greater Boston Stabilization Project - Results and Evaluations, 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Ford Foundation - Special Termination Benefits, 1974-1976 (Box 34, Folder 355)
  - The National Arts Stabilization Fund, Inc. - Personnel Handbook, 1993 January 1 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Agenda and Minutes of Meeting of Long-Range Committee, Including Appendices, 1992 March 18 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - National Arts Stabilization Fund - Staff Salaries, 1985-1986 (Box 34, Folder 356)